world. CHAPTER 16 I WON'T!" SAID MARY They found a great deal to do that
morning and Mary was late in returning to the house and was also in such a
hurry to get back to her work that she quite forgot Colin until the last
moment. "Tell Colin that I can't come and see him yet," she said to Martha. "I'm very
busy in the garden." Martha looked rather frightened.
"Eh! Miss Mary," she said, "it may put him all
out of humor when I tell him that." But Mary was not as afraid of him as other
people were and she was not a self-sacrificing person. "I can't stay," she
answered dickens's waiting for me;" and she ran away. The afternoon was even
lovelier and busier than the morning had been. Already nearly all the weeds were
cleared out of the garden and most of the roses and trees had been pruned or
dug about. Dickon had brought a spade of his own and he had taught Mary to use
all her tools, so that by this time it was plain that though the lovely wild
place was not likely to become a "gardener's garden" it would be a
wilderness of growing things before the springtime was over. "There'll be apple blossoms and
cherry blossoms overhead Dicken said, working away with all his might and
there'll be peach and plum trees in bloom against the walls and the grass
will be a carpet of flowers." The little fox and the rook were
as happy and busy as they were, and the robin and his mate flew backward and
forward like tiny streaks of lightning.
Sometimes the rook flapped his black wings and soared away over the Treetops
in the park. Each time he came back and perched near Dickon and CED several
times as if he were relating his adventures, and Dickon talked to him just
as he had talked to the robin. Once when Dickon was so busy that he did not
answer him at first suot flew onto his shoulders and gently tweaked his ear with his large
beak. When Mary wed wanted to rest a little Dickens sat down with her under a
tree and once he took his pipe out of his pocket and played the soft strange
little notes and two squirrels appeared on the wall and looked and
listened that's a good bit stronger than th was Dickens said, looking at her as
she was digging that's beginning to look different, for sure." Mary was glowing with
exercise and good spirits. "I'm getting fatter and fatter every day," she said quite
exultantly. "Mrs. Medlock will have to get me some bigger dresses. Martha says my
hair is growing thicker. It isn't so flat and stringy." The sun was beginning to set and
sending deep gold colored rays slanting under the trees when they
parted. "It'll be fine tomorrow said Dickon. "I'll be at work by sunrise." "So will I," said
Mary. She ran back to the house as quickly as her feet would carry her. She
wanted to tell Colin about dickens's fox cub and the rook and about what the
springtime had been doing. She felt sure he would like to hear. So it was not very
pleasant when she opened the door of her room, to see Martha standing waiting for
her with a doleful face. "What is the matter?" she asked. "What did Colin say when
you told him I couldn't come hey said Martha, "I wish they'd gone. He was nice
going into one of his tantrums. There's been an nice to do all afternoon to keep
him quiet. He would watch the clock all the time." Mary's lips pinched themselves
together. She was no more used to considering other people than Colin was
and she saw no reason why an ill-tempered boy should interfere with
the thing she liked best. She knew nothing about the pitifulness of people
who had been ill and nervous and who did not know that they could control their
tempers and need not make other people ill and nervous, too. When she had had a
headache in India she had done her best to see that everybody else also had a
headache or something quite as bad. And she felt she was quite right; but
of course now she felt that Colin was quite wrong. He was not on his sofa when
she went into his room. He was lying flat
on his back in bed and he did not turn
his head toward her as she came in. This was a bad beginning and Mary marched up
to him with her stiff manner. "Why didn't you get up?" she said. "I did get up this
morning when I thought you were coming," he answered, without looking at her. "I
made them put me back in bed this afternoon. My back achd and my head achd
and I was tired. Why didn't you come?" "I was working in the garden with
Dickon," said Mary. Colin frowned and condescended to look at her.
"I won't let that boy come here if you go and stay with him instead of coming to
talk to me," he said. Mary flew into a fine passion. She could fly into a passion
without making a noise. She just grew sour and obstinate and did not care what
happened. "If you send Dickon away, I'll never come into this room again!" she
retorted. "You'll have to if I want you," said Colin. "I won't!" said Mary. "I'll make
you," said Colin, "They shall drag you in."
"Shall they, Mr Raja said Mary fiercely.
"They may drag me in but they can't make me talk when they get me here. I'll sit
and clench my teeth and never tell you one thing. I won't even look at you. I'll
stare at the floor!" They were a nice agreeable pair as
they glared at each other. If they had been too little street boys they would
have sprung at each other and had a rough and tumble fight. As it was, they
did the next thing to it. "You are a selfish thing!" cried Colin. "What are you?"
said Mary. "Selfish people always say that anyone is selfish who doesn't do what
they want. You're more selfish than I am.
You're the most selfish boy I ever saw." "I'm not!" snapped Colin. "I'm not as
selfish as your f f Dickon is! He keeps you playing in the dirt when he knows
I'm all by myself. He's selfish, if you like!" Mary's eyes flashed fire. "He's nicer
than any other boy that ever lived!" she said. "He's— —he's like an
angel!" It might sound rather silly to say that but she did not
care. "A nice angel!" Colin sneered ferociously. "He's a common cottage boy off the
mall He's better than a common r retorted Mary. "He's a thousand times
better!" Because she was the stronger of the two she was beginning to get the
better of him. The truth was that he had never had a fight with anyone like
himself in his life and, upon the whole, it was rather good for him, though
neither he nor Mary knew anything about that. He turned his head on his pillow
and shut his eyes and a big tear was squeezed out and ran down his
cheek. He was beginning to feel pathetic and sorry for himself— —not for anyone
else. "I'm not as selfish as you, because I'm always ill, and I'm sure there is a
lump coming on my back," he said. "And I am going to die
besides." "You're not!" contradicted Mary unsympathetically. He opened his eyes
quite wide with indignation. He had never heard such a thing said before. He was at
once furious and slightly pleased, if a person could be both at the same
time. "I'm not?" he cried. "I am! You know I am!
Everybody says so." "I don't believe it!" said Mary sourly.
"You just say that to make people sorry. I believe you're proud of it. I don't
believe it! If you were a nice boy it might be true— —but you're too nice
nasty!" In spite of his invalid back Colin sat up in bed in quite a healthy
rage. "Get out of the room!" he shouted and he caught hold of his pillow and threw
it at her. He was not strong enough to throw it far and it only fell at her
feet, but Mary's face looked as pinched as a nutcracker. "I'm going," she said. "And I
won't come back!" She walked to the door and when she reached it she turned
around and spoke again. "I was going to tell you all sorts of nice things," she
said. "Dickon brought his fox and his rook and I was going to tell you all about
them. Now I won't tell you a single thing!" She marched out of the door and
closed it behind her, and there to her great astonishment she found the trained
nurse standing as if she had been listening and, more amazing still— —she was
laugh laughing. She was a big handsome young woman who ought not to have been a
trained nurse at all, as she could not bear invalids and she was always making
excuses to leave Colin to Martha or anyone else who would take her
place. Mary had never liked her, and she simply stood and gazed up at her as she
stood giggling into her handkerchief. "What are you laughing at?"
she asked her. "At you two young ones," said the nurse. "It's the best thing that
could happen to the sickly pampered thing to have someone to stand up to him
that's as spoiled as himself;" and she laughed into her handkerchief
again. "If he'd had a young vixen of a sister to fight with it would have been
the saving of him." "Is he going to die?" "I don't know and I don't care," said
the nurse. "Hysterics and temper are half what ails him." "What a asked
Mary. "You'll find out if you work him into a tantrum after this— —but at any
rate you've given him something to have hysterics about, and I'm glad of
it." Mary went back to her room not feeling at all as she had felt when she
had come in from the garden. She was cross and disappointed
but not at all sorry for Colin. She had looked forward to telling him a great
many things and she had meant to try to make up her mind whether it would be
safe to trust him with the great secret. She had been beginning to think
it would be, but now she had changed her mind entirely. She would never tell him
and he could stay in his room and never
get any fresh air and die if he liked! It would serve him
right! She felt so sour and unrelenting that for a few minutes she almost forgot
about Dickon and the green veil creeping over the world and the soft wind blowing down from the
Moore Martha was waiting for her and the trouble in her face had been temporarily
replaced by interest and curiosity. There was a wooden box on the
table and its cover had been removed and revealed that it was full of neat
packages. "Mr. Craven sent it to you," said Martha. "It looks as if it had picture
books in it." Mary remember remembered what he had asked her the day she had
gone to his room. "Do you want anything— —dolls— —toys—
—books?" She opened the package wondering if he had sent a doll, and also wondering
what she should do with it if he had. But he had not sent one. There were
several beautiful books such as Colin had, and two of them were about gardens and were full of
pictures. There were two or three games and there was a beautiful little writing
case with a gold monogram on it and a gold pen and ink
stand Everything was so nice that her pleasure began to crowd her anger out of her
mind. She had not expected him to remember her at all and her hard little heart grew quite
warm. "I can write better than I can print," she said, "and the first thing I shall
write with that pen will be a letter to tell him I am much obliged."
If she had been friends with Colin she would have run to show him her Presence
at once, and they would have looked at the pictures and read some of the
gardening books and perhaps tried playing the games, and he would have
enjoyed himself so much he would never once have thought he was going to die or
have put his hand on his spine to see if there was a lump
coming. He had a way of doing that which she could not bear. It gave her an uncomfortable
frightened feeling because he always looked so frightened himself. He said that if he felt even
quite a little lump someday he should know his hunch had begun to
grow. Something he had heard Mrs. Medlock whispering to the nurse had given him
the idea and he had thought over it in secret until it was quite firmly fixed in his
mind. Mrs. Medlock had said his father's back had begun to to show its
crookedness in that way when he was a child. He had never told anyone but Mary
that most of his "tantrums" as they called them grew out of his hysterical hidden
fear. Mary had been sorry for him when he had told
her. "He always began to think about it when he was cross or tired," she said to
herself. "And he has been crossed today Perhaps— —perhaps he has been thinking
about about it all afternoon." She stood still, looking down at the carpet and
thinking. "I said I would never go back again—" she hesitated, knitting her brows—"
—"but perhaps, just perhaps, I will go and see— —if he wants me— —in the morning.
Perhaps he'll try to throw his pillow at me again, but— —I think— —I'll
go." CHAPTER 17 A